<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An historical epistle of the great amitie and good offices betvvixt the popes of Rome, and kings of Great Britanie. Written to King Iames soone after his coming into England. / By Richard Smith ...</title>
            <author>Smith, Richard, 1566-1655.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B10051</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 80923759</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4153</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R184318</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">80923759</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 80923759</idno>
            <idno type="VID">192011</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B10051)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 192011)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; 1641-1700 ; 2897:36)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An historical epistle of the great amitie and good offices betvvixt the popes of Rome, and kings of Great Britanie. Written to King Iames soone after his coming into England. / By Richard Smith ...</title>
                  <author>Smith, Richard, 1566-1655.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The third edition somevvhat augmented.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>imprinted 1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College (Dublin, Ireland) Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Religion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:192011:1"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:192011:1"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST HIHGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE IAMES, BY THE GRACE OF GOD, KING OF GREAT Britanie, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>1. <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F ſaint Paul (moſt gratious ſouerai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gne) being accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of the whole Synagogue of the Iewes, by their Orator Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullus, of diuers heynous cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, both againſt Gods and the Princes laws, found notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſuch equitie in the Heathen Preſident Feſtus, as hee anſwered his aduerſaries, <hi>that is was not the cuſtome of the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 25.</note>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:192011:2"/> 
               <hi>Romans, to condemne any man before he haue his accuſers preſent, and place to make his anſwer:</hi> and alſo ſuch fauour at the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 26.</note> Iewish King Agrippa, as he both licenſed him to ſpeak for himſelfe, and afforded him fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorable audience: much more cauſe haue your Majeſties Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick ſubjects, being accuſed of Miniſters by their hired ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſman Bel, to expect the like yea greater fauour and equitie at your Graces hands. For if Romans, though heathens, thought it injuſtice to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn a particular man at the clamours of a whole Nation, before his accuſers were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and his defenſe were heard: and if Agrippa, albeit a Iew, and enemie to Chriſtians,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:192011:2"/> deemed it notwithſtanding a Princes part, to giue audience to one accuſed of that religion, which he both hated and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, how much more will a Chriſtian Prince forbear to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the vniuerſal cauſe of his Catholick ſubjects, for the ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and outcries of Miniſters, and one hired Proctor, before their Accuſers be brought face to face, and they haue time and place granted to anſwer for themſelues? Wherein wee shall account our ſelues more happie then Saint Paul, becauſe wee shall plead our cauſe, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Heathen or Iewish Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, but before a Chriſtian King, and ſuch a one, as better know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the queſtions and cuſtoms of Chriſtians, then King Agrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:192011:3"/> did of the Iews.</p>
            <p>2. Wherefore, ſeing of late one Th. Bel, (a fugitiue once from the Proteſtant religion, as he is now from Catholick) hath not onely accuſed, but alſo maliciouſly slandered the vniuerſal Catholick cauſe, in a booke, which he hath dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to your Maieſtie, and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it <hi>the Downfal of Poperie,</hi> and withal challengeth, dareth, and adjureth (in which caſe our Bleſſed Sauiour, though <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 26.</note> whith manifeſt danger of his life, made anſwer) al Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Prieſts, al English Ieſuits, and (as he ſpeaketh) Ieſuited Papiſts, to anſwer him, I haue preſumed vpon your gracious fauour to accept his challenge, and am readie to performe it
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:192011:3"/> hand to hand, if your Majeſtie grant licence, and in the mean time to dedicate to your Name, this my Confutation of his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, and ſlanders, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I ſpeake not for my ſelfe, as did Saint Paul before King Agrippa, but for the religion of your own Progenitors, and Predeceſſors, for the faith of your forefathers, for the cauſe of all Catholicks, and for the good, (I dare ſay) of your own Majeſties perſon and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes. For though Bel calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niate Chriſtian Kings and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, with opening a window to all Antichriſtian tyrannie, and Catholicks generally, with thinking Chriſt to be killed a thouſand times a day, and ſuch like, yet eſpecially he ſlande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:192011:4"/> the Popes, with vſurping power proper to God, and to depoſe Princes, and diſpoſe of their Kingdoms at his pleaſure, for to alienate your minde thereby, from the ſea Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick: wherein he not only abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth your patience with telling you palpable vntruths, but alſo greatly harmeth and endam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mageth your perſon and realm, by endeauouring by his fals ſlanders, to auert your minde from the Popes, who haue been the moſt ancient, moſt aſſured, and moſt beneficiall freinds, which the Kings and realms of great Britanie haue euer had. Which thing that I may make manifeſt vnto your Majeſtie, I humbly beſeech you giue me leaue to ſet downe ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:192011:4"/> examples, of the mutuall amitie, and kinde offices, which haue been betwixt the Popes and the Princes of this land. Wherein, if I bee ſomewhat longer, then men vſe to be in Epiſtles, I hope the varietie and profit of the mattaer will make requitall.</p>
            <p>3. Not long after the ſea A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolick <note place="margin">S. PETER P.</note> was ſetled in Rome, Saint Peter, the firſt Pope about the ſixtie third year of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lippoman</hi> 29. <hi>Iunij tomo</hi> 5.</note> CHRIST, <hi>came</hi> (ſaith <hi rend="sup">a</hi> Simeon Metaphraſtes, a Grecian writer about 800. years ago) <hi>into Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanie, where hauing ſtayed long time, and conuerted many nations vnto Chriſt, he ſaw an Angel, who tould him, that the time of his departure was at hand, and therefore he shold return to Rome,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:192011:5"/> 
               <hi>where being crucified, he should re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue the reward of iuſtice. When therefore he had glorified God, and giuen thanks, and ſtayed ſome daies with the Britans, ſetled Churches, and ordered Bishops, Prieſts, and Deacons, in the twelft year of the Emperour Nero, hee returned to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Metaphraſt. liued. Ann.</hi> 859. <hi>Baron. ibidem.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Rome.</hi> Thus much Metaphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes: all which he profeſſeth <hi>to haue taken out of ancient monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and to haue been publickly related.</hi> And withall addeth; <hi>that Euſeb. Pamphili</hi> (the ancienteſt Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtoriographer) <hi>reporteth, that Peter was twelue years in the Eaſt, and twenty three years in Rome, and in Britanie, and in the cities of the Weſt.</hi> So that, not onely Metaphraſtes, but alſo Euſebius teſtifieth, that Saint Peter came into Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tannie.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:192011:5"/> Neither hindreth it, that this teſtimonie of Euſebius is not found in any of his books now extant. For (as S. Hierom. ſayeth) <hi>he wrote innumerable vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes,</hi> which now are perished, in ſome whereof might be this teſtimonie. For it is no way li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kelie, that Metaphraſtes should feigne it; both becauſe he is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a ſaint, and honoured of the Grecians as ſuch, and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Councel of Florence, as a man of great authoritie; as alſo, becauſe there was no cauſe to moue him to feigne it; and laſtly becauſe hee might bee juſtly laughed at for feiging a thing wherein hee might bee eaſily diſprooued. And that ſaint Peter came into Britanie, not only English Catholicks, as
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:192011:6"/> Harpesfield lib. 1. hiſtor. cap. 2. <note place="margin">Grecians, Italians, French, Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards, Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians, Scots, En<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glish, ſay Saint Peter vvas in Britanie.</note> Broughton lib. 1. cap. 24, and others doe affirme, but alſo ſtrangers, as Iulianus Petri in Aduerſariis, §. 495. Baronius Anno 46. and his Epitomizers, Spondanus, Bzouius, Biſiola, Bernardus Iunius in Chronico Morali anno 46. Biuarrus in Chronico Dextri Anno 46. Ciaconus in vita Sancti Petri, Guillimannus in ſuis Habpur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicis lib. 2. cap. 1. Eiſeingrenius Centuria 7. par. 7. diſ. 8. Cheſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus in hiſt. Angl. l. 3. Poſſeui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus in apparatu tom. 3. Leſleus in Paraeneſi ad Scotos: And alſo learned Proteſtants con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the ſame. For thus Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bden <note place="margin">Proteſtants confeſſo it.</note> in his Britanie p. 52. <hi>Of the credit of Simeon Metaphraſtes,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Cambden.</note> 
               <hi>and the Greeks Meneologie, our</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:192011:6"/> 
               <hi>Eccleſiaſticall writers report, that Peter came hither, and ſpread the light of the Goſpel.</hi> And in his Remains pag. 4. <hi>The true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion was planted here by Ioſeph of Arimathia, Simon Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotes, Ariſtobulus, yea by ſaint Peter and ſaint Paul, as may bee proued by Dorotheus, Theodoretus, Sophronius.</hi> Spede lib. 6. cap. 9.
<note place="margin">Speed.</note> 
               <hi>Some ad, that S. Peter the Apoſtle preached the word of life in this Iland, as to others Gentils hee did, for whom God had choſen him, that from his mouth they might heare the Goſpel, and beleeue, and that he here founded Churches, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained Prieſts, and Deacons, which is reported by Simeon Metaphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, out the Greeke Antiquities.</hi> The like hath Vsher in his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquities <note place="margin">Vsher.</note> of Britanie c. 1. and 16.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:192011:7"/> And alſo Baker in his hiſtorie of <note place="margin">Baker.</note> England pag. 3. Who addeth, that <hi>this and more is reported by Authors of good credit.</hi> And I ad that no graue Author denieth it; nor can any ſufficient rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be brought, why it should not be beleued. So that, mere inctedulitie or obſtinacie can bee oppoſed againſt it, which may be oppoſed againſt anie hiſtorical writing whatſoeuer; and ſo all hiſtorical belieef ouerthrowne. For who beleue in hiſtories, what they will, and what they will not, beleue not, doe not beleue hiſtories, but themſelues.</p>
            <p>4. Neither was this loue of S. Peter to our countrie extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guished <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2. Petri</hi> 1.</note> by his death, but as himſelfe promiſed to ſome, he
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:192011:7"/> had it in minde alſo after his departure, and miraculouſly aſſiſted it in great neceſſities. So that truly wrote <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Malmeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Pontificum p.</hi> 209.</note> S. Sergius firſt Pope, one thouſand years ago, to our English Kings, that <hi>S. Peter was mindfull of them.</hi> And Pope
<note n="c" place="margin">Eugubin de Donat. Conſtan.</note> Alexander II. to King William the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and Pope <note n="d" place="margin">S. Peter Protector of Enhland.</note> Alexander III. to King Henry the ſecond, that <hi>England was vnder ſaint Peters protection, euer ſince Chriſts name was glorified there.</hi> And Pope <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bede lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 10. <hi>Huntington lib.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 317.</note> Boniface I. writing to King Edwin, calleth S. Peter, his Protector. For when our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie (about the year of Chriſt 611.) began to reuolt from the faith of Chriſt, and ſome Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops had forſaken the land, and S. Laurence Archbishop of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:192011:8"/> Canterburie was minded to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them, <hi>Saint Peter appearing</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Peter committed Englishmen to S. Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</note> 
               <hi>to him, and ſcourging him with sharp ſtripes, a great while in the cloſe night, chalenged with Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical authoritie, and asked him, why hee would forſake the flocke which he himſelfe had committed to him, and to what shepheard run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning now away, he would leaue the sheep of</hi> IESVS-CHRIST, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet in the midſt of ſo many woulues. By thes ſtripes of ſaint Peter, and with theſe exhortations, Laurence, being ſtirred vp and encouraged, came boldly to the king early in the morning, and looſing his garment shewed him how ſore hee was beaten, and how pitifully his flesh was torn. The King, as ſoone as he heard that for his own ſaluation the Bishop had ſuffered ſuch greuous</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:192011:8"/> 
               <hi>beatings, yea and that of the Apoſtle of</hi> CHRIST, <hi>he feared much, and afterward abandoning all worship of Idols, he embraced the Faith of</hi> CHRIST, <hi>and being baptized, endeauoured to keepe and maintaine the eſtate of the Church in al points to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of his power.</hi> Thus S. Bede lib. 2. c. 6. who liued in the ſame age, in which this happened; and the ſame teſtifieth the king himſelf, in his <note n="g" place="margin">Reiner. in Apoſt.</note> charter yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant. Alſo Alcuin in Epiſt. 97. and our beſt Hiſtoriographers, as William Malmeſburie lib. 1. Regum Angliae cap. 1. Henrie of Huntington lib. 3. pag. 326. Marianus in Chronic. ann. 617. Florentius Anno 616, Weſtmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſterienſis anno 616. And the <note place="margin">Proteſtants confeſſ it.</note> ſame is confeſſed by Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:192011:9"/> as by Bishop Godwin, in the life of S. Laurence, Holinshed lib. 5. hiſtor cap. 24. Iſacſon ann. 616. Weuer in his monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments pag. 245. who alſo ibid. pag. 246. rehearſeth the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphe vpon the tombe of ſaint Laurence, in which the ſame is affirmed, and laſtly, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gdeburgenſian Centuriatours Centuria 7. cap. 10.</p>
            <p>5. Not long before this, when <note place="margin">S. Peter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated VVeſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Church.</note> Sebareth, King of the Eaſt-Saxons, had built a Church in honor of S. Peter, in the place where now Weſtmonaſterie ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, ſaint Peter came from Heaven, and himſelfe dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated the Church, and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med his dedication by a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, which long after conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued. Authors of this, are two
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:192011:9"/> ancient and holy kings Edgar, <note place="margin">VVitneſſe, tvvo En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Kings, and graue Authors.</note> and S. Edward the Confeſſor, in their Charters made to that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſterie, as may be ſeen in Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop Vsher in his booke de Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mordiis Eccl. Britannicae cap. 16. pag. 741, 742, and in vveuer in his Monuments pag. 450. Whereof I will rehearſe the words of S. Edwards Charter, taken (as weuer ſaieth) outof the records of the Toure. <hi>The Church of S. Peter in Weſtminſter, was anciently builded vnder Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit, first Bishop of London, fellow and of the ſame time with Saint Austin first Archbishop of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburie, and by bleſſed Peter him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, with ſeruice of Angels, dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated with the imprinting of the holie Croſs, and vnction of the holie Trinitie.</hi> And king Edgar,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:192011:10"/> as Bishop Vsher relateth, in his Charter auoucheth, that <hi>in the year</hi> 604, <hi>it was dedicated, not of anie other, but of S. Peter himſelf Prince of the Apostles, to his own honor.</hi> The ſame certifie ſaint Ealred, <hi>a moſt graue Author,</hi> (ſaieth Spelman) in the life of ſaint Edward, the Author of ſaint Dunſtans life, William of Malmeſburie lib. 1. Regum, and lib. 2. Pontificum, Capgraue in life of S. Edward, Otterburn, Walſingam an. 1378, pag. 213. and 214. Baronius an. 610. And are not two ancient and holie kings, and ſo many graue au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors worthie to bee beleued? <note place="margin">S. Peter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stored the royal En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish blood, to the crovvn.</note> Likewiſe, when the Danes had oppreſſed England, vſurped the crowne, and driuen all the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:192011:10"/> royal English blood out of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, Saint Peter appeared in a viſion, to Brithwold, a holy Bishop of Wilton, or (as ſome ſay) of Wincheſter, anointed ſaint Edward king of England, and foretold the yeares of his reigne, and the end of the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the Danes, adding theſe moſt confortable words: <hi>The</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Our best Authors te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie it.</note> 
               <hi>kingdome of England, is the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God.</hi> Authors of this, are the aforeſaid Malmeſburie lib. 2. Regum cap. 13. and lib. 2. Pontif. pag. 249. Ealred in life of ſaint Edward. Weſtmonaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienſis anno 1056, Capgraue in life of S. Edward, Polidor. lib. 8, Harpesfeld ſaec. 11. cap. 19. Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronius an. 1043. And it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed
<note place="margin">Proteſtants confeſſe it.</note> by Proteſtants, as by Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:192011:11"/> Parker in vita Stigandi, by Bishop Godwin in vita Brith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woldi, by Cambden in his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains pag. 5, Holinshed lib. 7. cap. 15, by Iſaakſon anno 909. and others.</p>
            <p>6. Neither was the ſingular affection towards our countrie, peculiar to ſaint Peter, but (as from a fountain) deſcended to his ſucceſſors. For when the ſweet ſound of the Goſpel here preached by him, had in time increaſed, and come to the ears of Lucius, then king here, he ſending to Rome for Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, <note place="margin">P. ELEV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THERIVS</note> Pope Eleutherius the fourteenth Pope after Saint Peter, about the year <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gordo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> 188</note> 186, <note place="margin">P Eleuthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius Legats conuert Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanie.</note> ſent hither ſaint Fugatius and Damian, who inſtructed, and baptized the King, Queen, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:192011:11"/> moſt of the people, whereby our countrie became the firſt, which publickly profeſſed the faith of CHRIST, as teſtifieth the learned Pamelius, in his notes vpon Tertullian againſt the Iewes, and the ſame ſaieth <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Leſlcus, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 27.</note> Sabellicus Enneade 7. lib. 5, and thsrefore iuſtly deſerueth the title of <hi>Primogenita Eccleſiae.</hi> This teſtifie <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Damaſus in Pontific. Harpesfield ſaec.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</note> ſaint Bede lib. 1. cap. 4, the Roman Martyrologe 26. Maij, and the Breuiarie on the ſame day, Marianus in Chronico, Huntington lib. 1. pag. 304, Ethelwerd an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient writer of the blood royal, lib. 1. Weſtmonaſterienſis anno 188, and it is confeſſed by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, <note place="margin">Proteſtants confeſſe it.</note> as by Bale Centuria 1. cap. 22, Cambden pag. 628, Cooper anno 180, Godwin in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:192011:12"/> life of ſaint Auſtin, Stow anno 179, Parker in Archiepiſcopis
<note place="margin">P. VICT. I. <hi>P. Victor I. Legatt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </note> pag. 4. The like charitable of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice performed Pope Victor I. vnto Scotland, ſending thither his Legats at the requeſt of king Donaldus, who baptized the King, Queen, and his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, as teſtifie Boeth lib. 6. hiſt. Scotiae fol. 86. Genebrardus in Chronico, Holinshed in the hiſtorie of Scotland pag. 72, and others. And about the year 324. Pope Silueſter, hauing <note place="margin">P. SIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VESTER anno 324.</note> perfectly inſtructed our great Emperor Conſtantin, bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed him, and cured him of his leproſie, as the ſame Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in his edict, and manie
<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Monolog. Graec. Cal. Iun. Acta Liberi vita Silueſtri Huntington l.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 306. <hi>Elerentius anno</hi> 506.</note> others teſtifie. Likewiſe about the year of CHRIST 400, <hi>Ninian, beeing taugth at Rome</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:192011:12"/> (ſaieth S. Bede lib. 3. cap. 4.) <hi>truly the faith, and myſteries of truth, was</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Capgraue in his life. S. Ninian Legat of the P. conuerted the Picts.</note> 
               <hi>thence ſent to conuert the ſouth Picts,</hi> who then inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited the beſt part of Scotland. And about the year 429, Pope Celeſtin conſecrated Palladius,
<note place="margin">P. CELE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STIN I.</note> Bishop, and ſent him into Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, where as yet was no Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop; nor forgetfull of Ireland, ſent thither that great ſaint Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trik <note place="margin">S. Patrik, Legat of P. Celeſtin, conuerted Ireland.</note> who conuerted that Iland to the true Catholick Faith, and is therefore iuſtly termed euen of <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cambden in Hibernia</hi> 760. <hi>Bale Centur.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 44. <hi>S. Germrn Legat of</hi>
               </note> Proteſtants, <hi>the Apoſtle of Ireland.</hi> And whereas, at the ſame time, the Britons began to be infected with the hereſie of Pelagius, the ſame
<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Celestin ſuppreſſed Pelagian. in Britan.</hi> p <hi>Proſper in Chro. Baro. anno</hi> 429.</note> Pope ſent ſaint German, and ſaint Lupus, to confute, and ſuppreſſe that hereſie, which they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:192011:13"/> both with diſputations and miracles. Thus continued the exceeding loue of the ſea Apoſtolick vnto great Brita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, al the time, that the Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons poſſeſſed it al, or the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part thereof.</p>
            <p>7. But towards our English Nation, after it had conquered that part of great Britanie, which now is called England, it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red far greater. For whereas, not only the <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bede lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</note> Britons refuſed, but alſo al neighbour nations <note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>S. Gregorie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ib.</hi> 5. <hi>Epiſ</hi> 58. 59.</note> neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, to preach the Chtiſtian faith to our English anceſtours, who euer before had been Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, and <hi>bondſlaues</hi> (ſaieth ſaint Bede) <hi>of Idols,</hi> only Rome
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> put forth her helping hand to draw them out of darknes <note place="margin">P. GRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GORIEI. anno 599.</note> and ſlauerie of Idols. For no
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:192011:13"/> ſooner, <hi>that bleſſed and holie Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, S. Gregorie,</hi> (as Bishop
<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>In life of ſaint Auſtin p.</hi> 3.</note> God win calleth him) vnderſtood, that the <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bede lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Ioan. Diacon. in vita Creg.</hi>
               </note> Angles, or English (whom for their beutie hee termed Angels) were Pagans, but forth with he went to the Pope of that time, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeched him to ſend Preachers into England, offering him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be one. And obtaining licence thereof came on his voyage three dayes iournay to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards England; but was recal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led at the great importunitie of the Romans, who were vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to want ſo worthie a man. But neuertheles he forgot not his holie entrepriſe. <hi>For as ſoone</hi> (ſaieth ſaint Bede lib. 2. cap. 1.) <hi>as he was Bishop ouer the whole world, he made our nation the</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:192011:14"/> 
               <hi>Church of</hi> CHRIST, <hi>which had been euer vntill that time, the bondſlaue of Idols.</hi> And in the year 596. ſent hither S. Auſtin, with almoſt fortie Monks more to preach; who being enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by king Ethelbert, in short time conuerted both him, and his whole countrie. And that they preached the true faith of CHRIST, appeared by the miracles which they wrought in teſtimonie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which were ſo manie, and ſo great, <hi>as it ſeemed</hi> (ſaieth ſaint Gregorie) <hi>that they imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the vertues of the Apoſtoles by the miracles which they wrought;</hi> and they are ſo certain and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted, as they are not only teſtified by the ſayed S. <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 9 <hi>epiſt.</hi> 56. 58.</note> Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie, S. <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 32. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1. 2.</note> Bede, and other an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:192011:14"/> Authors, but confeſſed euen by the moſt earneſt
<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Fox in Acts p.</hi> 105. <hi>Godvvin in life of ſaint Auſtin. Stovv in Chro. p.</hi> 65. <hi>Holinshed lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 19. 21. 20. <hi>Spelman in Concil. p</hi> 93. <hi>Cambden p.</hi> 104.</note> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants. Again, in the year 601, he ſent more Preachers, and with them, al things neceſſarie for the ornament and ſeruice of the Church, <hi>as holie veſſells,</hi> (ſaieth ſaint Bede lib. 1. cap. 29.) <hi>altar clothes apparel for Prieſts and Clerks, Reliks of holie Apoſtles and Martyrs, and many books:</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. <hi>Gregor. ſent. a Pall for Maſs.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and a Pall to S. Auſtin to vſe only,</hi> (ſaieth S. Gregorie) <hi>at Maſs,</hi> appointed him to be ouer al the Bishops and Prieſts of Britanie, and gaue him licence to inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute two Archbishopricks, and 24, Bishopricks. Beſiids, he ſent rich preſents of diuers kindes to the King and Queen, and alſo ſent order into France to buy <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Greg. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>epiſt.</hi> 10.</note> ſuch Engliſh youthes,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:192011:15"/> as were there ſlaues, and to ſend them vp to Rome, there to be brought vp in wertue and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; wherein he gaue the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the English Seminarie, which not long aftet our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish kings founded in Rome. Such was the exceeding loue of this bleſſed Pope towards our nation, <hi>whom we may wel, and muſt</hi> (ſaieth Saint Bede lib. 2. cap. 15.) <hi>call our Apoſtle, and may lawfully pronounce of him, that ſaying of the Apoſtle: Although he were not an Apoſtle to others, yet he was to vs, for the ſigne of his Apoſtleship, we are in our Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>8. Neither was this great good, ſo happily begun, and planted in our nation by ſaint Gregorie and his Legats, neglected by the Popes his ſucceſſors, but
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:192011:15"/> rather diligently watered and furthered by them, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by the letters and meſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of diuers of them ſent vnto our Princes, and Bishops to that purpoſe; as of Pope Boniface in the year 618. of Pope Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius <note place="margin">P. HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIVS I. anno 635.</note> in 633, of Pope Agatho 679, Pope Zacharie 746, Pope Adrian 789, an others. But moſt of all it was increaſed by Pope <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bede l.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>Godvvin in vita Birini. Parker in Antiquit. cap.</hi> 10. <hi>Cooper an.</hi> 636. <hi>Ball centur.</hi> 13. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. P. VITA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAN anno 668.</note> Honorius his ſending hither in the year 635, that Apoſtolical man S. Birin who conuerted the Weſt-Saxons; and by Pope
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bede l.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Godvvin in vita Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dori. Parker in vita Theod.</hi>
               </note> Vitalian, who in 668, ſent hither thoſe holie and great learned men Saints Theodore and Adrian, by whoſe teaching, Englishmen, in short time, became the beſt learned of rhat age, and were
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:192011:16"/> the beginners of the <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gordon anno</hi> 791 <hi>Genebrard. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ib</hi> 3. <hi>ſaec</hi> 8. S. <hi>Antonin. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ib.</hi> 14. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>Palmerius anno</hi> 791. <hi>Spondanus anno</hi> 1334. <hi>Boſsius l.</hi> 21. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ap.</hi> 6. P. LEO III <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nno 808. <hi>Amoinus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 94. <hi>Regino in Chron. Baronius anno</hi> 808.</note> Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of Paris, and conſequently the chiefeſt fountain of learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which ſince hath been in the Weſt. After this, Eardulf, king of the North beiond Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, being driuen out of his kingdome and countrie, Pope Leo III. in the year 808. ſent Cardinal Adulf his Legat into England, who by the help of Charles the gteat his Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours, reſtored him peacebly, <note place="margin">P. LEO IV an. 847. <hi>or</hi> Gregor. 4. anno 817.</note> into his kingdome. Not long after, Pope Leo IV. <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Malmeſb. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 2. <hi>Pontif. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 242. <hi>Baronius anno</hi> 847.</note> diſpenſed with King Ethelwoulph, for to marrie, which he (being a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacon) could not otherwiſe doe lawfully. And at the ſame Kings requeſt, crowned his ſonne
<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aſſerius in vita Alfredi Ethelvverd lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>Malmeſbur. l.</hi> 2. <hi>Reg. c.</hi> 2. <hi>Stovv p.</hi> 99.</note> Alfred king, adopting him for his ſonne; who after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:192011:16"/> for his moſt worthie acts, both in war, and peace, was ſurnamed <hi>the great,</hi> and for al things, became the rareſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, <note place="margin">P. MAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIN I. anno 883. <hi>Florentius anno</hi> 884. <hi>VVeſtmon. anno</hi> 883. <hi>Godvvin in vita Pleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundi p.</hi> 17.</note> that England, (and perhaps Chriſtendome) euer had. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, Pope Martin, at the ſute of the ſame King Alfred, relea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the tribute, which the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Seminarie then in Rome paied, and ſent to the King manie gifts, amongſt which, was a good peece of the holie croſs.</p>
            <p>9. In the year 990, when Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Marquis of Normandie, had purpoſed to inuade En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, and make war vpon king Ethelred, Pope <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ihon</hi> xv. <hi>anno</hi> 990. g <hi>Malmeſb. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Reg. cap.</hi> 10. <hi>p.</hi> 64. <hi>Baronius anno</hi> 990.</note> Ihon XV. ſent his Nunce, and letters to take vp the matter, who hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily brought them to aggree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:192011:17"/> And about the year 1059. <note place="margin">P. NICO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAS II. anno 1059</note> Pope Nicolas II. granted to king Edward the Confeſſor, and to his ſucceſſors the
<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Surius in vita ſancti Edvvardi Bale Cent.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 52. <hi>Capgraue in vita sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cti Edvvardi.</hi> P. VR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BAN II. anno 1094.</note> aduouſion and protection of the Churches in England. And in the year 1094. Pope Vrban II. in a councel at Bari, appointed, that S. Anſelm Archbishop of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburie, and his ſucceſſors, should ſit in Councels beſide the Archdeacon of Rome, who ſitteth before the Pope, adding this moſt honorable ſpeech: <hi>let</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Malmeſbur. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Pontif. p.</hi> 223. <hi>Godvvin in vita An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelm, latine.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>vs include in our compaſs this man, as Pope of an other world:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as before it was vnkown (ſaieth Malmeſburie) what place be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to our Archbishop. And the ſame place did Pope Paſchal <note place="margin">P. PAS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHAL II. anno 1102. <hi>Malmeſhur. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Pont. p.</hi> 224.</note> II. confirme in a Councel at Rome, about the year 1102.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:192011:17"/> And beſides this, diuers others dignities, and priuiledges haue been granted to the ſea of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburie, by the Popes, as to be Primats of al Britanie, Legat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> born, and the like.</p>
            <p>10. Moreouer, in the year 1098. the Scots obtained of <note place="margin">P. VR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BAN II. anno 1098. <hi>Genebrard. in Chron.</hi>
               </note> Pope Vrbain II. for their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, that hee might haue the name, title, and anointment of a King, as the <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Baronius anno</hi> 1000. <hi>Bale Cent.</hi> 2. <hi>part.</hi> 145.</note> Hungarians and Polonians had obtained for their Princes, about the year 1000. wherupon King Edgar was then firſt anointed King of Scotland. And about the year 1107, Pope Paſchal II. <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Malmeſb. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Reg. p.</hi> 163. <hi>Gordn anno</hi> 1101. <hi>Boeth lib.</hi> 2. <hi>fol.</hi> 261.</note> writing to king Henrie I. amongſt other things, promiſeth ſo to fauour him and his ſonne, as <hi>what</hi> (ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth he) <hi>hurteth you or him, may</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:192011:18"/> 
               <hi>ſeem to hurt the Church of Rome.</hi> And in the year 1152. when king
<note place="margin">P. EVGE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NIVS III. anno 1152. <hi>Stovv anno</hi> 1152. <hi>Godvvin in vita Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bald.</hi> P. ADRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>AN IV. anno 1160. <hi>Par. an.</hi> 1155 <hi>Bale Cent.</hi> 2. <hi>Giraldus Cambrenſ. in Hibern. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. Io. <hi>Sariſbur. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 42. <hi>Stovv anno</hi> 1160. <hi>Cambden in Hibern. p.</hi> 762. <hi>Parker in vita</hi> S. <hi>Tho.</hi> P. ALEX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ANDER 3. anno 1171. <hi>Houeden lib.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 528. P. LV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIVS III. anno 1183. <hi>Houeden lib.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 628.</note> Stephn, hauing vſurped the crown of England, endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to cauſe the Bishop to crown his ſonne Euſtace, thereby to exclude for euer the lawfull heyr, Henrie II. Pope Euge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius III. ſent commandment to the Clergie, not to medle in that matter; whereby it was hindred. In the year 1106, Pope Adrian IV. gaue vnto King Henrie II, the dominion and gouernment of Ireland, and ſent vnto him the Bull of his grant, with a ring of gold in token of the inueſtiture. Which grant, at the requeſt of the ſaid king, Pope Alexander III. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed to him and his heirs. And as for Pope Lucius III, his
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:192011:18"/> good will appeareth by the great praiſe, which he giueth to the ſaid king Henries anceſtours, whom he affirmeth to haue far exceded the reſt of chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in warlik power, and noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of minde. Which affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on continued alſo in his ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor Pope Vrban III. of whom <note place="margin">P VR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BIN III. anno 1185. <hi>Houeden lib.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 631. <hi>Stovv anno</hi> 1185.</note> the ſaid king Henrie the ſecond obtained manie things, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of one was, that hee might crown which of his ſonnes he would, King of Ireland; which he confirmed by a Bul, and in token of his good wil and grant, ſent him a crown. And laſtly when not only the King of France, but alſo his own ſonnes, and nobles, had conſpired a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſaid king Henrie II, and had inuaded his dominions
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:192011:19"/> withfar greater power, then he <note place="margin">P. CLE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT III. anno 1189. <hi>Houeden lib.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 652. <hi>VVeſtmon. anno</hi> 1189.</note> was able to reſiſt, Pope Clement III, in the year 1189, ſent a Cardinal to procure peace, who excommunicated the hinderers of peace, and threatned to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdict the kingdom of France, vnles the king made peace with England.</p>
            <p>11. Likewiſe in the year 1193, when king Richard I. was taken priſoner, as he came from the holie land, by the Duke of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria, <note place="margin">P. CELE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STIN III. anno 1193. <hi>VVeſtmon. anno</hi> 1193. <hi>Houeden p</hi> 773. <hi>Polid. l.</hi> 14. <hi>Paris anno</hi> 1195. <hi>Stovv anno</hi> 1195.</note> Pope Celeſtin III, at the ſaid kings requeſt, excomuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated the Duke, and enioyned him to releaſe the couenants, which hee had compelled the king to make, and to ſend home the pledges: Who not obeying the Pope, he ſoone dyed miſerably, and was left
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:192011:19"/> vnburied vntil his ſonne had ſent home the pledges, and ſworn to ſtand to the iudgment of the Church. And in the year <note place="margin">P. INNO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CENT III anno 1207. <hi>Paris anno</hi> 1207. <hi>Stovv anno</hi> 1207.</note> 1207, Pope Innocent III. ſent to king Ihon an eloquent Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, and diuers pretious jewels: And in the year 1215, when the Barons had extorted from the ſaid king, certain <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Paris ann.</hi> 1216. <hi>Polidor. l.</hi> 15. <hi>Stovv anno</hi> 1215. <hi>Godvvin in vita Steph. Lang. Bale Cent.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 260.</note> charters, and liberties, the ſame Pope, at the kings requeſt, diſannul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thoſe charters, and excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated the Barons, who had rebelled againſt him. And when the ſaid Barons had cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in Lewis the Prince of Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>King Ihon put al his hope in the Popes Legat. Paris anno p.</hi> 377.</note> choſen him their king, and yeelded the chiefeſt cities and holds into his hands, ſo that England was in manifeſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to be loſt, the ſaid Pope
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:192011:20"/> ſent his Legat to aſſiſt king Iohn, and to forbid the French vpon paine of excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to enter into England, which he ſtoutly performed, and was a great means of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueing England. In the year <note place="margin">P. INNO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CENT IV anno 1258. <hi>Paris anno</hi> 1254. <hi>Stouv anno</hi> 1254.</note> 1258, Pope Innocent IV. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed the royal title of the kingdomes of Naples and Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilie, vpon Edmund ſonne to king Henrie III, and by a Cardinal, ſent to him the inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiture <note place="margin">P. ALEXANDER IV. anno 1257. <hi>VVeſtmon. anno</hi> 1254. <hi>Bale Cent.</hi> 4 <hi>p</hi> 290. <hi>Paris anno</hi> 1254.</note> thereof. And in the year 1257, Pope Alexander IV. ſent meſſengers to Richard Duke of Cornwal, brother to the ſaid king Henrie, for to goe into Germanie to receaue it, which he did, and was crowned at Aquiſgran. And in the year 1292, when the Barons had
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:192011:20"/> wreſted from the ſaid King Henrie 3, certain liberties, Pope Vrban IV, at the ſaid kings re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, <note place="margin">P. VR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BAN IV. anno 1292. <hi>Stovv anno</hi> 1262. <hi>Bale Ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi> 4. <hi>p</hi> 293. 326. <hi>Paris p.</hi> 1322</note> ſent a Legat to accurſe thoſe Barons, who had rebelled in defenſe of thoſe liberties.</p>
            <p>12. In the year 1272, at the petition of king Edward I. Pope Gregorie X. excommunicated
<note place="margin">P. GRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GORIE X anno 1272. <hi>VVeſtmon. anno</hi> 1272. <hi>Polidor. l.</hi> 17 <hi>VValſinga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ypodig. anno</hi> 1273.</note> Guy of Montfort, for killing the kings couſin germain in his return from the holie land, condemned him of wilful and priuie murder, of ſacriledg and treaſon; declared him to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous and incapable of anie office in the commonwealth, diſinherited his poſteritie to the fourth generation, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated al thoſe, who entertained him, and interdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted their dominions. And in
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:192011:21"/> the ſame Kings time, was <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Camden in Canta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brig p</hi> 435.</note> Cambridge, of a ſchole, made on vniuerſitie by the Pope. And vnder Edward II. Pope Clement V. apointed, that in Oxford should be read two Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Clement tit. de Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giſtris cap.</hi> 1.</note> of the Hebrew, Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bick, and Chaldaick tongues, and authorized it for one of the foure famouſeſt Vniuerſities in Chriſtendome. Alſo in the year 1316. Pope Ihon XXII. at the <note place="margin">P. IHON XXII. anno 1316. <hi>Polidor l</hi> 17 <hi>Stovv anno</hi> 1316. <hi>VValſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gam. anno</hi> 1312. 1317.</note> ſaid king Edward II. his requeſt, ſent two Legats to make peace betwixt England and Scotland, and to reconcile Thomas Earle of Lancaſter to the king; who excommunicated the Scots, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they would not aggree to peace, And in the ſame year, at the ſame kings petition, the Pope confirmed al the ancient
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:192011:21"/> priuiledges of the Vniuerſitie of Cambridg, which of long time they had enjoyned, <hi>by the benefit</hi> (ſaieth <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1317.</note> Stow) <hi>of the Popes predeceſſors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>13. Moreouer in the year 1489, Pope Innocent VIII. <note place="margin">P. INNO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CENT VIII. anno 1489. <hi>Godvvin in Epiſc. Bathon. n.</hi> 42.</note> ſent a Nunce to appeaſe the the diſſenſion betwixt the king of Scotland and his people, but before his arriual, the king was ſlain. And about the year 1504. when there aroſe a contention betwixt king Henrie VII. and Ferdinand king of Spain, about precedence of their Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours <note place="margin">P. IVLIVS II. anno 1504. <hi>Spondanus anno</hi> 1433. <hi>Volateran. Comin ventura. Stovv</hi> 1505 <hi>Bacon. in Henrie</hi> 7.</note> with the Pope, Pope Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius II. hauing heard both Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours, gaue ſentence in favour of the king of England. And in the year 1505. ſent to the king, a ſword and cap of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:192011:22"/> maintenance, as to a defender of the Church. But as no king of England deſerued better of the ſea Apoſtolick, then King Henrie VIII. did for long time, ſo none receaued more honor from thence then he. For he receaued not only from <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Stavv anno</hi> 1514.</note> Pope Iulius II, in the year 1514. a ſword and cap of maintenance, for defending him againſt the king of France, but alſo of <note place="margin">P. LEO X. anno 1521. <hi>Stovv in Chron. Onuphrius in Chron.</hi>
               </note> Pope Leo X, in the yeat 1521, the moſt honorable title of DEFENDFR OF THE FAITH, for his writing againſt Luther. Which title, as it is more hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable then the title of moſt Chriſtian, or Catholick, giuen by Popes to the kings of France and Spain, ſo was it euer moſt highly eſtemed by king Henrie,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:192011:22"/> and <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Stovv anno</hi> 1547.</note> engrauen on his tombe, where is left out the title of his ſupremacie.</p>
            <p>14. And though Queen Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth had vtterly caſt of the Popes freindship, yet he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoke not her. For Pope Pius <note place="margin">P. PIVS IV. anno 1560.</note> IV. ſuppoſing, that she had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolted from that ſea, rather for fear that her title to the crown might be called in queſtion, becauſe one Pope before had declared her birth to be vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, then for diſlike of the reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which in her fathers and ſiſters days, she had profeſſed, ſent à Nunce to promiſe her al fauour touching her title to the crown, and <note n="p" place="margin">1562.</note> ſoone after, an other to requeſt her to ſend her Deuines to the Councel of Trente, with promiſe of al ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:192011:23"/> and libertie. Neither <note place="margin">P. CLE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT VIII. anno 603.</note> may I leaue your Maieſtie out of the number of the Princes of this land, who haue taſted the loue of the ſea Apoſtolick, becauſe out of your own grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful minde, you haue
<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at. anno <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>egni.</hi> 1.</note> publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profeſſed your ſelf behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den vnto Pope Clement VIII, <hi>for his temporal cariage and diuers kind offices towards you.</hi> Beſids, he hath (as is reported) cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured al ſuch, as shal moleſt your grace, and hath often times profeſſed, that he would willingly giue his life for the eternal good of your countrie, which is the greateſt loue, that one can bear, (as our Sauiour teſtifieth) to his freind. Oh how great enemies are they vnto England, who ſeek by fals ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:192011:23"/> to make ſuch freinds odious vnto vs.</p>
            <p>14. By this which hath been ſaid, (omitting much more for breuitie) your Maieſtie cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeeth, how greatly, and how continually, the ſea Apoſtolick hath euer fauoured the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Princes of this land: how manie, and how great benefits, both ſpititual and temporal, Popes haue beſtowed vpon them, and in their dangers and diſtreſſes, according to their power, aſſiſted them, <note place="margin">Popes haue more bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited Engl. then al Chriſtde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ome hath done.</note> Weigh (I beſeech your grace) in the balance of your prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie wiſedome, the foreſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, with ſuch, as your ſelf or anceſtours haue receaued from the reſt of Chriſtendome, and you shal finde, that the ſea Apoſtolick alone, hath more
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:192011:24"/> benefited England, then al Chriſtendome beſids, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, that the forſaking the Popes freindship, hath more endammaged your realm, then if it had forſaken the reſt of Chriſtendome. But eſpecially (I humbly beſeech your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie) weigh them with ſuch, as Bel or anie Miniſter can shew you to haue receaued from their two ſeats of peſtilence, in Wittenberg and Geneua. What kingdoms haue they beſtowed vpon you? vnto what Imperial or Royal dignitie haue they exalted you? from what Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme haue they conuerted you? what enemies haue they appeaſed? what aſſiſtance haue they afforded you in any need? what good, litle or great, haue they
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:192011:24"/> brought to this land? Nay what miſchiefe haue they not brought? That one Apoſtata &amp; firebrand of ſedition, Knox, ſent from Geneua, brought more miſchief to your grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother, your B. Mother, to your Father, and Kingdome of Scotland, then I can rehearſe, or your Majeſtie without great griefe can remember. Miniſters pretend the loue of the Goſpel, as the cauſe of perſuading you from freindship with the Pope: but yet diſſuade not from
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cenference at Hampion court p.</hi> 80. 81.</note> freindship with the Turke. They pretend alſo your Graces ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie; but the true cauſe indeed, your Majeſtie deſcried and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered in Knox, to wit, their own ſecuritie and aduanceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which they fear would be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:192011:25"/> if you kept your an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and ſureſt freind, and therefore with your loſſe (as your Majeſtie perceaued in your Grandmothers caſe) they worke their owne wealth and ſecuritie. And thus much of the Popes.</p>
            <p>15. As for the Chriſtian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this land, though they haue been of foure different, and moſt oppoſite nations, to wit, Britons, English, Danes, and Normans: yet haue they al aggreed in keeping the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue of freindship with the Pope, being officious vnto him, and accounting him their eſpecial freind. Of the British kings of <note place="margin">K. LV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIVS.</note> this land, firſt is king <note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Beda lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> Lucius, whoſe particular affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſea Apoſtolick, is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by that, he neglecting
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:192011:25"/> other Chriſtian Churches neer <note place="margin">CONS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TANTIN <hi>the Great.</hi>
               </note> vnto him, he ſent ſo far as to Rome for preachers. As for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantin the great (the immortal glorie of rhe British kings) his extraordinarie loue and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction vnto the ſea of Rome is more notorious, then I need rehearſe. For he not only gaue vnto the Pope, the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Rome, and of a good part of the Weſt, (as beſids <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>In edicto. Eugubin dc Donat. Conſtant. Genebrard. in Chron. Ciaconus in S. luest.</hi> 1. <hi>Victorellus in notis ad Ciac.</hi>
               </note> himſelf and Latin Hiſtriogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, both <note n="t" place="margin">Photius in Nomocan.</note> Greecks, and
<note n="u" place="margin">Abraham Abben Efra.</note> Iewes profeſſed enemies to the Pope doe teſtifie) but alſo ſerued him as a lackey, holding his ſtirrop, and leading his horſe by the bridle. Cad wallader alſo the laſt British king in England <note place="margin">K. CAD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VALA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DER ann. 652.</note> hauing left his countrie went no whether but to Rome, and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:192011:26"/> there ended his days. And if the hiſtories of thoſe ancient times were more perfect, or the Britons had raigned longer in this Iland, no doubt but wee should haue more examples of their deuotion to the ſea Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicke, as appeareth by Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <note place="margin">K. SALO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MON. <hi>Argentreus hiſt. Britan. lib</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 27. <hi>Baron. anno</hi> 869.</note> their king in litle Britanie, after they had been driuen hence by the Saxons, who wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to Pope Adrian II. begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his letter thus. <hi>Domino ac beatiſsimo Apoſtol. ſedis Rom. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>driano, Salomon Britannorum rex, flexis genibus, inclinatoque capite.</hi> And ſendeth him his ſtatua in gold with diuers rich gifts and money, promiſeth a yearly pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and acknowledgeth his Royal title to haue been giuen to him by Popes. This was the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:192011:26"/> loue of the British king vnto the ſea Apoſtolick.</p>
            <p>16. To the British kings ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded the Saxons or English as wel in their loue and reuerence to the ſea of Rome as in their <note place="margin">K. ETHEL<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>BERT anno 597.</note> Kingdome. For king Ethlebert, at the verie firſt, receaued ſaint Gregorie his Legats verie cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly, prouided them of al things neceſſarie and freely li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed them to preach, vſing theſe gracious words, worthie to be imitated of your Majeſtie, <hi>For ſo much as you are come ſo far to impart vnto vs ſuch know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, as you take to be true, we wil not trouble you, but rather withall courteſie receaue you.</hi> After him, king Oſuin, hauing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly <note place="margin">K. OSVIN anno 665.</note> learned, that <hi>the Church of Rome</hi> (ſaieth ſaint Bede) <note place="margin">
                  <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:192011:27"/> 
               <hi>was the Catholiek and Apoſtolick Church,</hi> ſent thither in the year 665 a Prieſt to be conſecrated Archbishop of Canterburie. And in a conference about the obſeruation of Eaſter, hearing, that the keyes of heauen were giuen to S. Peter, concluded thus: <hi>I will not gainſay ſuch a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>b.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 25. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aronius <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nno</hi> 664.</note> 
               <hi>Porter, as this is, but as far as I know, and am able, I wil couet in al points to obey his ordonnance.</hi> And in the year 670. <hi>He bare</hi> (ſaith S. Bede) <hi>ſuch loue and affection to the Apoſtolick ſea of Rome, as if he might haue eſcaped his ſicknes, he purpoſed to goe to Rome, and to end his life in thoſe holie places there.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>17. But what he could not through death perform the valia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> CED<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ALLA <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>no 6; 9.</note> Prince Cedwalla did in the verie
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:192011:27"/> flour of his age, and proſperitie. For in the year 689, <hi>Forſaking his kingdome</hi> (ſaieth ſaint Bede) <hi>he went to Rome thinking it to be a ſingular glorie, and renoune for him to be regenerated with the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crement of Baptiſme, at the ſea Apoſtolick: and withal conceaued hope, that as ſoone as by baptiſme he was cleanſed from ſinne he should depart from this world to immortal ioy:</hi> Which by Gods prouidence was performed, and he honorably buried, by the Pope in S. Peters Church. Not long after him to wit in the year 709. two English kings, Coen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and Offa, forſooke their <note place="margin">K. <hi>Coenred</hi> 3706. K. <hi>Offa.</hi>
               </note> kingdoms, went to Rome, and there became Monks, <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuing</hi> (ſaieth ſaint Bede) <hi>at the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 10 K. <hi>Ina ann</hi> 726.</note> 
               <hi>tombes, in praying, fasting,</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:192011:28"/> 
               <hi>and dealing alms vntil their dying</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap. ij Baronius anno</hi> 729. <hi>Ethelvverd lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 13. <hi>Malmeſbur. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Reg. cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Polidor l.</hi> 4. <hi>Stovv in Ina. p.</hi> 96.</note> 
               <hi>day.</hi> Ina, alias Hun, ſucceſſor to king Cedwal in his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſucceded him alſo in his deuotion to the ſea Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick. <hi>For after he had raigned</hi> (ſaith Bede) 37. <hi>years, he gaue ouer his kingdome, and went him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the tombs and monuments of the Apoſtles in Rome, as in thoſe dayes manie English, both of the Nobilitie, and Commons, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and temporal, men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, were wont to doe with great emulation.</hi> Neither went he on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to Rome, but became there a Monke, and was the firſt, that paied the Peter pence, appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that euerie houſeholder of <note place="margin">K. Ina gaue the Peter pence.</note> his kingdome, who had thirtie pennie worth of cattle of one ſort, should pay yearly one
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:192011:28"/> pennie to Rome. Which mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>English Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minarie in Rome</hi> 900 <hi>years ſince VVeſtmon. anno</hi> 727. 764.</note> was partly for the Popes vſe partly for maintenance of an English ſchole or Seminarie, which he then built in Rome, for bringing vp of English youths there in vertue and learning.</p>
            <p>18. Not long after, about the year 750, ſaint Richard king <note place="margin">K. RI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHARD <hi>anno</hi> 750. <hi>Surius to.</hi> 1. <hi>Baronius anno</hi> 750.</note> forſoke his kingdome, and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his two ſonnes in Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, with ſaint Boniface an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glisman, the Popes Legat there, went himſelf in pilgrimage to Rome, but dying in the way at Luca, is there honorably buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And the year 775, king <note place="margin">
                  <hi>K. Offa anno</hi> 775. <hi>Malmesbur. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Reg. cap.</hi> 4. <hi>VVeſtmon. anno</hi> 194. <hi>Polidor l.</hi> 4. <hi>Fox p.</hi> 101.</note> Offa, though a warlick Prince, went to Rome, and imitating the example of king Ina, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed the English Seminarie
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:192011:29"/> begun by him, and impoſed the like penſion of Peter pence, vpon his kingdome of Mercia: as Charles the great, about the ſame time, impoſed vpon Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce the like tribute to be paied to Rome. The loue and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of king Kenulph, a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie <note place="margin">K. KE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NVLPH anno 808. <hi>Malmeſbur. l.</hi> 1. <hi>Keg. c.</hi> 4. <hi>Baronius anno</hi> 828.</note> Prince, and ſucceſſor to king Offa, appeareth by his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeming the Popes Legat, taken of Pirats, in the year 808. and by his ſubmiſſiue letter to the Pope, wherein he humblie cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth his bleſſing, as al his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors had, deſireth to be adopted for his ſonne, as <hi>I</hi> (ſaith rhe king) <hi>loue you like a father, and embrace you with al obedience.</hi> And proteſted to be willing to ſpend his life for the Pope.
<note place="margin">K. ETEL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VVOLPH anno 855.</note>
            </p>
            <p>19. After him king Ethelwolph,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:192011:29"/> in the year 857. went to Rome, tooke with him his beſt beloued ſonne Alfred, to be inſtructed (ſaith Weſtmonaſter) <hi>of the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>VVeſtmon. anno</hi> 854. <hi>Ethelvverd lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>Stovv anno</hi> 839. <hi>Ingulfus Bale Cent.</hi> 2 <hi>p.</hi> 113. <hi>Aſſerius in vita afredi.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Pope in manners and Religion</hi> where he aboad a whole year, and procured his ſonne to be crowned of the Pope, and ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted of him for his ſonne: he alſo notably repaired the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glith Seminarie at Rome, which had been burnt a little before, &amp; confirming the guifts of king <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Malmeſbur. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Reg. cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Stovv anno</hi> 839. <hi>Fox p.</hi> 136.</note> Ina and Offa, impoſed the pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Peter pence vpon al En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, which was afterward paid vntil the later end of King Henrie VIII. About the ſame <note place="margin">K. BVR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DRED <hi>Ethelvverd lib.</hi> 4 <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>Malmeſbur. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>Stovv anno</hi> 875.</note> time king Burdred leauing his kingdome went to Rome, and was there buried in the English ſchole. Neither would King
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:192011:30"/> Canute, though a Dane, be <note place="margin">K. CANV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TE anno 1032. <hi>Florent. anno</hi> 1031. <hi>Matmeſbur. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 11. <hi>Ingulfus. Huntington lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Marian. anno</hi> 1033, <hi>Stovv in Canute.</hi>
               </note> found vngratefull to the ſea Apoſtolick, but went to Rome, in the year 1032, confirmed the payment of the Peter pence, gaue great gifts of gold and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and pretious things to ſaint Peter, and obtained of Pope Iohn immunitie for the English Seminarie. And finally, King Edward Confeſſor, laſt but one, of the Saxon bloud, would haue <note place="margin">K. EDVV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ARD <hi>son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor. Ealred in vita Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvardi. Baronius anno</hi> 1060.</note> gone to Rome in pilgrimage, had not his people vpon fear of the Danes inuaſion, hindred him; yet ſent he Embaſſadors to Rome, with great preſents, and confirmed al the duties and cuſtomes belonging thereto in England. And thus continued the English Kings, al the time of their raign, in ſingular affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:192011:30"/> and deuotion to the ſea Apoſtolick.</p>
            <p>20. To whom, as the Norman <note place="margin">K VVIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAM Conquer. anno 1066. <hi>Malmeſbur. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Reg. Ingulfus p.</hi> 900. <hi>Stovv in Harald. p.</hi> 131.</note> Princes ſucceded, ſo they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them in their pietie and religion. For beſids, that they paied the Peter pence, in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Willam the Conquerour, having ſubdued and ſlain king Harald in the year 1066, ſent <note place="margin">K. HEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIE I. <hi>Malmeſbur. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Pontif. pag.</hi> 226. K. HEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIE II. anno 1180. <hi>Rob. Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſis. Genebrard. anno</hi> 1180. <hi>Sigebertus anno</hi> 1163. <hi>Neubrigenſ. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 14. <hi>Bale Cent.</hi> 2 <hi>cap.</hi> 94. <hi>Holinſhed anno</hi> 1163. <hi>Baronius anno</hi> 1162.</note> ſtraight his ſtandard to the Pope as to his particular freind. And king Henrie I. profeſſed by his Embaſſadour to Pope Paſchal II. that England was <hi>a peculiar prouince of the Church of Rome, and paied vnto her yearly tribute.</hi> King Henrie II. about the year 1180, together with Lewis king of France led Pope Alexanders horſe, and with great pompe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ducted him through the citie
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:192011:31"/> Tociacum. King Richard, Coeur <note place="margin">K. RI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHARD I <hi>Polid. l.</hi> 14. <hi>Genebrard. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n Chron. Stovv. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ale Cent.</hi> 2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 104. <hi>Houeden</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 609.</note> de Lion, at the exhortation of the Pope, went in perſon to the holie land with an armie of thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thouſand foot, and fiue thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand horſe: in which voyage he conquered the kingdome of Ciprus, and citie of Ptolemais, and ouerthrew the Souldan in a great battel; and the like en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe afterward tooke king Edward I. in the year 1241. King <note place="margin">K. HEN<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>RIE III. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tovv anno</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>241.</note> Henry III. placed the Popes Legat in the moſt honorable roome of the table at a publick banquet in Chriſtmas betwixt himſelf and the Archbishop of Yorke: and afterward <hi>with great pompe</hi> (ſaith Stow) <hi>and innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable companie of nobles, and trumpets ſounding before brought him to the ſea.</hi> How deuout king
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:192011:31"/> Richard II. and Englishmen <note place="margin">K. RI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHARD II. <hi>Stovv anno</hi> 1407.</note> in his time were to the ſea of Rome, appeareth by their buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding an hoſpital there for receit of English Pilgrims, inſtead of the foreſaid Seminarie, which (as it ſeemeth) was deſtroyed in that great burning of Rome in the year 1084.) in the place whereof S. Thomas of Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie had before built a Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel in honour of the bleſſed Trinitie. This Hoſpital was afterwards, in the raigne of king Henrie VI, and Henrie VII reedified, and much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, and laſtly in the year 1570 was much bewtified, and augmented both in buildings and reuenews by Pope Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie XIII, and by him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted to the ancient vſe of a
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:192011:32"/> Seminarie, retaining ſtil the obligation of an Hoſpital.</p>
            <p>21. The affection of King <note place="margin">K. HEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIE IV. <hi>Stovv anno</hi> 1409.</note> Henrie IV. appeareth by his letter to the Pope in the year 1409, which he beginneth thus: <hi>Moſt holie Father, our recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations in humble wiſe premiſed.</hi> And afterward; <hi>Hauing taken with our ſaid ſonne, and alſo with our Prelats and Nobles, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture deliberation, we beſeech with al humilitie, and require your cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie (whoſe ſtate and honor vpon diuers cauſes, as a deuout ſonne of the Church, ſo far as we might with God, we haue euer embraced, and doe embrace) by the expreſſe and whole aſſent of the eſtates afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, &amp;c.</hi> And as for king Henrie <note place="margin">K. HEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIE V.</note> V, he in the year 1416 ſent his Embaſſadours to the General
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:192011:32"/> Councel at Conſtance, at whoſe procurement <hi>it was there ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> (ſaith Stowe) <hi>that England</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Stovv</hi> 1416</note> 
               <hi>should obtain the name of a Nation, and be one of the fiue Nations, that owe their deuotion to the Church of Rome, which thing vntil that time, men of other Nations for enuie had</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Note this.</note> 
               <hi>letted.</hi> Behold, what an honor, king Henrie V, the Alexander of England, and Conquerour of France, in his moſt flourishing and triumphant time, accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it to owe deuotion to the Church of Rome; which now Miniſters would account ſo dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honorable. And for king Henrie <note place="margin">K. HEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIE VII. <hi>Bacon. in Henr.</hi> 7.</note> VII, your Majeſties great grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father; his affection is euident by the ſword and cap of main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance ſent to him from the Pope, anno 1505.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:192011:33"/>
            <p> 22. But none of the kings of <note place="margin">K. HEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIE VIII.</note> the Norman blood, euer shewed ſo great ſignes of loue and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to rhe ſea Apoſtolick, as king Henrie VIII, did for a long time. For firſt in the year 1511, he wrote to the French king, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt from moleſting Pope Iulius II, and in the next year, ſent an armie of ten thouſand men into <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Onuphr. in Iulio</hi> 2. <hi>Stovv anno</hi> 1511. 1512. 1513.</note> France for the Popes defence. And in the year 1513, he went himſelf in perſon, with a royal armie, and conquered Turwin, and Tournay. And not content to defend the Pope with his ſword, in the year 1521, wrote an excellent booke in his defence againſt Luther. And again, in the yeare 1527, when Pope Clement was taken priſoner by the Emperors ſoldiers, he gaue
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:192011:33"/> monthly 60 thouſand Angels, to the maintenance of an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, for the Popes deliuerie. And in this ſingular affection towards the ſea Apoſtolick, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued he vntil the 22 year of his raigne anno 1530, when not vpon anie iniurie offered by the Pope, or diſlike of his religion, which (except the matter of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie) he defended to his death, and perſecuted the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, but only <hi>vpon occaſion of delay</hi> (ſaith Stow) <hi>made by the</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Stovv anno</hi> 1530. <hi>&amp; ſeq.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Pope in his controuerſie of deuor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cement, and through diſpleaſure of ſuch reports, as he heard had been made of him to the court of Rome, and thirdly pricked forward by ſuch Councellers to follow the example of the Germans,</hi> he firſt forbad the procurement of anie thing
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:192011:34"/> from Rome, and ſoon after pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited al payme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, and appeals to Rome, and laſtly, tooke vpon him that ſupremacie, which al his Chriſtian predeceſſours had acknowledged to bee in the Pope.</p>
            <p>23. Thus your Majeſtie ſeeth, how long, how honorably, and how profitably alſo vnto both parties, hath the mutual amitie and league of freindship betwixt the ſea Apoſtolick, and the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of al the foure Nations, that haue ſwayed the Scepter of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued and flourished: and how of late it was broken by one Prince, vpon meer paſſion, contrarie to the example of al his predeceſſors, and ſucceſſors alſo, except one child, &amp; a woe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. What dangers &amp; troubles,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:192011:34"/> he and his kingdome incurred thereby, and how his progenie (according as Friar Paeto, and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Houſe anno</hi> 1533.</note> Elſton did then foretell him) is now conſumed, and his crown tranſlated to an other royal line, againſt which in his time he
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hungtinton lib.</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 359.</note> made verie sharp war, I need not heer declare. Only I will ſay, that himſelf, being after more free from paſſion, laboured to be reconciled to the ſea Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick, and employed therein Bishop Gardiner, (as he profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in a ſermon at Pauls Croſs) and had eaſily obtained it, if he would haue acknowledged his fault, and done penance. What remaineth for me to conclude this long Epiſtle, but proſtrat at your Majeſties feet, humbly to beſeech you, for your own good,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:192011:35"/> and in the name of the foreſaid Chriſtian Princes, as you are the head of the 5 natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <note place="margin">Hungtinton ſupra.</note> to Gods prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, foretold by a holie man manie years ago) hath attained to the rule of the land, ſo you would continue that moſt ancient, honorable, and profitable league of freind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, which was betwixt them al, and the ſea Apoſtolick. Who (I beſeech your grace) will giue you more faithful councel, then your own Progenitors and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers? Who can giue more ſafe and ſecure direction in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of your Kingdome, then your own predeceſſors, who ſo happily, and ſo long time gouerned it? who are ſo worthie to giue you example, or whom can you with ſo much honor
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:192011:35"/> imitate, as ſo manie, ſo valiant, ſo prudent Princes? And yet they al, with one voice, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel and requeſt you to follow in this ſo important a matter, not ſo much themſelues, as the counſel of the wiſeſt king, rhat euer was, yea of God himſelf, in theſe words: <hi>Thine owne freind,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prouerb. cap</hi> 27.</note> 
               <hi>and thy fathers freind, ſee thou forſake not;</hi> eſpecially ſuch a one, as hath euer been, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly your own freind, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly your bleſſed Mothers freind, but of al your Chriſtian forefathers, who as they haue left vnto your grace their crown and kingdome, ſo haue they alſo bequeathed their faith, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and freindship with the ſea Apoſtolick, as no ſmal por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſtay of their inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:192011:36"/> We eſteem your publick acknowledging of Rome to be the <hi>Mother Church;</hi> and your <note place="margin">Speech in the Rarlament</note> ſelf to be beholding to Pope Clement VIII, <hi>for his temporal cariage, and kinde offices,</hi> as ſparks of a greater fire of loue in kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Proclamat. An</hi> 1. <hi>regni.</hi>
               </note> in your princelie hart to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that ſea, which we beſeech Almightie God ſo to increaſe, as it may one day burſt forth to your own good, and the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal joy of Chriſtendome: Our Lord IESVS long preſerue your Majeſtie, with al grace, health, and proſperitie.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Majeſties dutiful ſubject and dailie Orator R. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
